

# Curriculum Vitae for Asmund Ødegård

#### **Personal information**

Address: Sneisveien 26 E-mail: asmund@xal.no

1407 Vinterbro Phone: +47 900 69 915

Born: 23.08.1972 Nationality: Norwegian

### Summary

I am a senior software developer, project leader, and researcher, with 19 years of professional experience. Most of my career prior to founding Expert Analytics AS together with Ola Skavhaug, has been with Simula Research Laboratory, ranked as Norway's best ICT research institution in 2012. Through various positions in that company I have obtained a broad set of technical and management skills, which I since 2013 has used as Managing Director and Senior Consultant in Expert Analytics. My main areas of technical expertise spans from mathematical software development and scripting, to administration of advanced ICT solutions and configuration management. Both through education and practical hands-on experience I have developed strong analytical skills within my fields of expertise.

As manager and leader of several projects with internal and external participants, I have learned the importance of understanding the strengths and skills of the participants in order to deliver on time. Communication within the team is always key to ensure that everyone have ownership in the project and stay motivated. This must always be balanced with a firm leadership.

#### **Technical skills**

Frameworks Google App Engine, Puppet, Numpy, Pandas, SciPy, MPI, BSP,

Diffpack, Plone, Knockout, jQuery, RequireJS, Web.py, Turbogears,

Bootstrap, Slim, Twig

Languages Python, C, C++, C#, PHP, Java, Javascript, Bash, Matlab, Languages Python, C, C++, C#, PHP, Java, Javascript, Bash, Matlab, Languages

HTML, Sql, CSS, Scala, Lisp

Tools Linux, OS X, VirtualBox, Vagrant, MySql, Sqlite, NoSqls, Apache,

Nginx, Git, Subversion, CVS, Mercurial, Make, SCons, Autoconf,

buildout

### **Education**

2006	Dr. Scient in Scientific Computing, Faculty of Mathematics and Na-
	tural Sciences, University of Oslo. Thesis' title "Applications of high
	level software for parallel solution of Partial Differential Equations."
1995	Cand. Scient in Applied and Industrial Mathematics, Department of
	Mathematics, University of Oslo

### **Professional experience**

2013 -	Managing Director and Consultant at Expert Analytics	
2011 - 2013	Director of External Research Funding at Simula Research Laboratory	
2010 - 2011	Director of Administration at Simula Research Laboratory	
2008 - 2010	Assistant Director of Administration at Simula Research Laboratory	
2005 - 2007	Research Scientist at Simula Research Laboratory	
2004 - 2009	IT Manager at Simula Research Laboratory	
2001 - 2005	Scientific Programmer at Simula Research Laboratory	
2000 - 2001	Scientific Programmer at Department of Informatics, University of	
	Oslo	
1996 – 1999	Research Assistant at Department of Informatics, University of Oslo	
1996	Summer intern, SINTEF Applied Mathematics	
1993 – 1994	Assistant teacher, Department of Mathematics, University of Oslo	

## **Extended descriptions of selected projects**

Activity	mCASH development
Role	Senior Python Developer
Staffing	12-15 developers

Description My responsibilities in this project included integrations of third-party

APIs for user-identification with Norwegian BankID, and development of APIs for access to mCASH resources for external integrators, based on OpenID Connect and Oauth protocols. I was also deeply involved in design and implementation of the transactional engine handling the payments; the core of the mCASH system. This engine connects persons, merchants and banks together, and computes transation fees for involved parties in addition to moving correct amounts. The backend system of mCASH is implemented solely in Python. The development

at mCASH followed the Scrum agile method.

Tools Python, Google app engine, webapp2, Jinja2, Javascript, jQuery,

HTML, Nose tests, Git, Jira.

Activity SmartBlikk development

Role Systems Architect and Senior Developer

responsibility was development of an API for the system for import of data from external systems, as well as integrating external APIs for use from SmartBlikk, mainly for importing accounting data. The pilot of SmartBlikk was created by the founder of Intelliview, and I am in charge of designing and implementing the second version of the system with dynamic in-browser reporting capabilities. I am also in charge of establishing a deployment environment for SmartBlikk on the cloud, specifically on Amazon Elastic Beanstalk scaling out with

multiple EC2 nodes and using AWS RDS database.

Tools Php, Mysql, Slim, Twig, Javascript, jQuery, AWS EB, AWS EC2, AWS

RDS.

Activity FrontSystems development Role Senior Developer and adviser

Staffing 3 developers

Description FrontSystems is a Norwegian company developing a web-based POS

system. The current system was build on some technologies that are approaching EOL, and my main role was to advise and contribute towards a more modern architecture. This include moving development and deployment to Github and Azure as well as implementing reporting services in POS backend using client-side JS rather than Microsoft

reporting services.

Tools C#, JavaScript, Asp.Net, Knockout, Bootstrap, RequireJS, jQuery,

MSSQL, TeamCity, Git, Azure.

Activity Building linux clusters

Role Project manager, lead architect and developer

Staffing 2 additional Systems administrators

Description For the scientific computing group at Ifi, University of Oslo and later at

Simula Research Laboratory, I was in charge of building three different compute clusteres for advanced numerical computations. The systems grew from 32 compute cores up to 576, and was configured with core os, multiple networks, schedulers and queue systems. The first clusters where managed with CFengine as provisioning system, while the last

one was provisioned using Puppet.

Tools Debian GNU/Linux, CFengine, Puppet, OpenPBS, MAUI, MPIch,

BSP,

Activity Demographic and financial estimations

Role Architect and main developer

Staffing Project leader, developer, front-end designer

Description For customer we developed a web-based tool for statistical estimation

of demographics within a large closed group, and a tool for economical planning of a large scale development. My main contribution was the mathematical analysis of the problem, and development of the necessary logic and algorithms. Further, I also implemented the system in a custom application server. The work was carried out in

close collaboration with financial experts and a designer.

Tools Python, Pandas, Web.py, Sqlite, MS Sql, Excel, HTML, CSS, Java-

Script, jQuery

Activity Establishing technical infrastructure of Simula Research Laboratory

Role Project leader and main architect

Staffing Project leader, 4 system administrators, external contractors

Description For the newly created research institute we designed and developed

a full technical infrastructure in the renovated office building at the old airport at Fornebu; office networks, back-end facilities and computer room, telephone systems, printers, servers, etc. Technical requirements, budgetary limitations and practical issues had to be taken into consideration in order to establish a scalable and flexible infrastructure.

Activity Symphonical Role Main developer

Staffing Project leader and two developers

Description Symphonical is a web-based collaboration tool. Initially it was conce-

ived as a tool for running agile software development projects based on the metaphor of post-it notes on a virtual wall, a scope that since has been widened. We created the first prototype of the system, in 2005, before it was spun out as a company and developed further by

others.

Tools PHP, MySql

Activity Simulation of Medical Ultrasound Role Researcher and main developer Staffing 4–5 researchers and developers

Description A research project where we studied different mathematical models

for numerical simulation of medical ultrasound. My main responsibility was implementation of object oriented finite element based simulators for ultrasound propagating in inhomogeneous media. The target

application was detection of tumors in tissue.

Tools C++, Diffpack, MPI, VTK

Activity PySE

Role Main developer and researcher

Description Python Stencil Environment (PySE) is a high level environment for

solving partial differential equations using finite difference methods (FDM). The environment provides an abstraction for the stencil concept of FDM, which makes it possible to implement FDM-based simulators in notation very close to the mathematical formulation. The environment is inherently parallell and distributes a problem on the available hardware in an optimal way based on the communication patterns defined by the stencils. PySE was developed as part of my

PhD studies and published as open source software.

Tools Python, Numpy, Scipy, SWIG, C++, MPI

Activity Python Computing Components (PyCC)

Role Developer

Description PyCC is a modern and efficient scripting framework that is used to

solve differential equations to study the electrical activity in the human heart. The main parts of PyCC is a high level scripting interface implemented in Python for flexibility and low-level extension modules implemented in C/C++ and Fortran for efficiency. My main role in the project was to provide a flexible build system for PyCC taking into account all the dependencies of the system. The build system was

implemented using the SCons framework.

Tools C/C++, Fortran, Python, Swig, MPI, Subversion, SCons, PETSc,

FEniCS, Hypre, BoomerAMG, Diffpack, GNU Compiler Collection and

Debugger

Activity Web site for Simula Research Laboratory

Role Main developer and designer

Description In order to facilitates new communication strategies for the company,

it was necessary to update the web site for Simula Research Laboratory. New channels for communicating news and ongoing research projects were created, as well as a complete redesign of the company Intranet which at the same time replaced mailing list as the primary form of official internal communication. The process of upgrading the system consisted both of technical work and meetings with all the stakeholders within the organisation in order to develop a system in line with their

needs

Tools Python, PHP, Javascript, Plone, MySql

Activity Outsourcing of ICT services

Role Project coordinator

Description Simula Research Laboratory decided in 2012 to put a contract for its

IT operations out for tender, after running the services with internal resources for a decade. My core responsibility was authoring the specification of the tender and evaluating the offers as well as participate in negotiating the final contract. I was also responsible for handling the communication with all the internal stakeholders. As the change affected the daily work of all employees it was particularly important to have an open and inclusive dialog in the process to ensure a satis-

factory result.

### Languages

English Fluent

Norwegian Mother tongue

#### Personal skills

Communication Writing and editing, typesetting & typography, try to learn French

Funding EU and RCN funding instruments, consortium development, proposal

writing

Management Development and implementation of strategies, guidelines and proce-

dures, lead and encourage staff, personnel follow-up

Technology Extensive knowledge about system administration; always eager to

learn about new frameworks and open source technologies; solution

architect and problem solver

### Some interests and hobbies

Hard Bicycle, motorcycle

Soft Playing clarinet and saxophone, cooking &wine, photography Tech Fonts, typesetting with TEX, computers, gadgets, coding